Paul Richards Collection Relating to Theodore Roosevelt
Paul Richards Collection Relating to Theodore Roosevelt
1898-1913
0.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, incoming and outgoing (1898, 1910-1913); memorabilia, including clippings, itineraries, and annotated maps; and typescript speeches, with revisions.
149542
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Paul Richards Collection Relating to Theodore Roosevelt consists of correspondence, memorabilia, and writings.
Correspondence includes incoming letters and telegrams, and carbons of outgoing letters. The bulk of the correspondence deals with Roosevelt's European and South American tours, and includes letters to and from his personal secretary, Frank Harper. Of particular interest is a group of letters to Henry Cabot Lodge in 1910 (April 6, 11 and May 14, 24) discussing Roosevelt's views on President William Howard Taft and the upcoming election. Letters to Andrew(?) Carnegie (April 22, 1910), Nicholas Longworth (May 14, 1910), and Elihu E. Root (April 27, 1910), and William Allen White (December 12, 1910) deal with similar matters. Also in the 1910 correspondence are telegrams from several members of European royalty: Victor Emanuel (Italy), Franz Joseph (Austria), Frederick (Denmark), and Gustav (Sweden). The death of Edward VII of England is noted by President Taft's telegram to Roosevelt designating him as the United States official representative at the King's funeral.
Roosevelt's letters to and from Charles Dwight Willard (April 28, 1911 to February 29, 1912) are long and detailed accounts of political and other considerations. The 1913 correspondence deals primarily with arrangements for Roosevelt's South American tour, but letters from William C. Liller of Indianapolis (September 30), Judge John R. Hazel of Buffalo, New York (October 2), and Frank L. Dingley of Lewiston, Maine (also October 2) provide interesting sidelights on Progressive Party matters from their particular regional viewpoints.
Some of the correspondence is in French, German, Hungarian, Portuguese, and Spanish, with a few messages in code and two items in shorthand.
Memorabilia includes clippings, ephemera, financial papers, itineraries and supporting material, membership certificates, and programs.
Roosevelt's Writings include his speech to the American Historical Association on December 12, 1912, titled "History as literature," as well as two other speeches. A very small quantity of fragmentary material is also included.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Memorabilia and Writings are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
See also the
Theodore Roosevelt Collection
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Richards, Paul, collector.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Politicians -- United States.; Presidents -- United States.; United States -- History, 1909-1913.; United States -- Politics and government, 1909-1913.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Itineraries.; Maps (documents); Speeches (documents); Politicians.; Presidents.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Paul Richards, 1968.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1898, 1910-1913, undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings, 1910; 1913 (Box 1)
  - Ephemera (Box 1)
  - Financial papers, 1910; 1913 (Box 1)
  - Itinerary, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Itinerary, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Maps, Berlin, Brazil, Paris (Box 1)
  - Membership certificates, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Programs, 1910; 1911 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - "History as literature," American Historical Association, Dec 27, 1912; original typescript, revised (Box 1)
  - "How England will deal with her land question", original typescript, revised (Box 1)
  - Untitled speech on the United States Post Office, original typescript (Box 1)
  - Untitled fragment (?), original typescript (Box 1)